Guide to the Frederic Shields Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Frederic Shields collection
1895-1912
GEN MSS 281
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.4
(1 box)
Correspondence with Mackenzie Bell concerning a Christina Rossetti biography, the decoration of the Chapel of the Ascension in London, and other matters; with letters to Bell concerning the Chapel of the Ascension fund and ten letters by Ernestine Mills about the life and work of Shields.
Other Storage Formats: [xx rolls, oversize folders, framed items, whatever]
Shields, Frederic, 1833-1911
Rossetti, Christina Georgina, 1830-1894
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from R. Metzdorf on the Daggett fund, 1957.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid lists manuscripts by or relating to Frederic Shields.
Pre-Raphaelites; Bell, Mackenzie, 1856-1930; Mills, Ernestine; Shields, Frederic, 1833-1911
- Shields Correspondence, 1902 Mar 2; Series I
  - Anderson, Rev. D. ALS to an unidentified recipient. London, 1902 Mar 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Regarding the agreement with Shields about the chapel decorations.
  - Bell, Mackenzie, 1856-1930. 15 ALS (holograph copies) to various recipients. London, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Concerning the Chapel of Ascension fund; Accompanied by a clipping from the Manchester Guardian for 1904 Jan 25 about the artist, a label addressed to Bell, and an index with the article marked.
  - Chapel of the Ascension. Typed draft of circular appeal for funds. London, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Accompanied by printed copy of circular, TLS from Hugh B. Chapman, author of the circular, to Mackenzie Bell and addressed wrapper.
  - Fitzgeorge, George William Adolphus. 3 ALS to Mackenzie Bell. London, 1904 Jan (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hunt, William Holman, 1827-1910. 2 ALS (Copies in the hand of Mackenzie Bell) to Frederic Shields. London, 1899-1900 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mills, Ernestine. 9 ALS and 1 TLS to Mackenzie Bell. London, 1911-12 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    About the Life and work of Frederick Shields; Accompanied by copies of 5 letters to Mrs. Mills from Mackenzie Bell and a newspaper clipping about Shield's drawings illustrating Defoe's Journal of the Plague Year.
  - Perowne, John James Stewart, 1823-1904. ALS to Mackenzie Bell. Southwark, Tewkesbury, 1904 Feb 9 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Seton, Sir Bruce. ALS to Mackenzie Bell. London, 1904 Feb 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sharp, William, 1855-1911. ALS to Frederic Shields. London, 1895 Jun 24 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Introducing Mackenzie Bell.
  - Shields, Frederic James, 1833-1911. 39 ALS, 6 APS, and 1 telegram to Mackenzie Bell, 1895-1911 (Box 1, Folder 10-14)
    Accompanied by copies of Bell's correspondence with Shields about the Christina Rossetti biography proofs, including 1 ALS dated 1896 Jun 30, the section of proof which Shields corrected, and several envelopes; Also accompanied by holograph copies of 2 ALS from Bell to Shields (1904 Oct 24, 1904 May 2), and also a list of letters sent to Bell by and about Shields.
  - Sinclair, William. 2 ALS to Mackenzie Bell. London, 1904 Mar (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Tull, William J. ALS to Mackenzie Bell. Thornton Heath, Surrey, 1912 Feb 10 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    About the death of Frederic Shields; Accompanied by 2 newspaper clippings regarding Shields' death.
  - Watts, George Frederic, 1817-1904. ALS (copy in the hand of Mackenzie Bell) to the trustees of Mrs. Russell Gurney, the originator of the chapel fund. Guildford, 1901 Jan 4 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Watts-Dunton, Theodore, 1832-1914. 2 LS to Mackenzie Bell. Putney, 1911 Nov (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Regarding a monument for Frederick Shields; Accompanied by a copy of a letter from Bell to Watts-Dunton.